Guide to the Francis C. Moon Reuleaux Reference Collection, 1841-2010
Moon, Francis C., Reuleaux Reference Collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Francis Charles Moon Reuleaux reference collection, 1841-2010
6960
F. C. Moon 1939-
6.2 cubic feet.
Correspondence, photographs, publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers regarding German engineer Franz Reuleaux and the collection of his kinematic models housed at Cornell University. Papers were assembled by Cornell Professor of Engineering Frank Moon during the late 1990's and early 2000's, particularly during research trips to Germany. They include Moon's research notes on Reuleaux and Reuleaux's influence, biography and genealogy; photocopies and transcriptions of letters, essays and drawings created by Reuleaux; Moon's academic papers and professional work on Reuleaux; and research on Cornell's kinematic model collection and other kinematic models. Papers also include material on specific projects, such as the permanent exhibit of Reuleaux's kinematic models at Cornell, and the Kinematic Models for Design Digital Library (KMODDL), an online collection of digitized images and information on kinematics.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Francis Charles Moon is the Joseph C. Ford Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering at Cornell University.
Franz Reuleaux (1829-1905), a German engineer of Belgian heritage, was an influential figure in machine design and kinematics, or the science of movement. He was known for designing more than 800 teaching models to demonstrate kinematic principles. He contributed to the development of engineering as a professional science, integrating mathematical and scientific principles into engineering design. Born in Eschweiler in Prussia, he studied under Ferdinand Redtenbacher at Karlsruhe, and also studied in Berlin and Bonn. After teaching in Zurich at the Polytechnic School, he taught at what became the Koenigs Technischen Hochschule in Berlin-Charlottenburg Berlin for many years, becoming its rector in 1890. As a prominent engineer, he was a German ambassador at international exhibitions and expositions, including the Philadelphia Centennial Exhibition in 1876 and the Vienna Exhibition in 1873.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers regarding German engineer Franz Reuleaux and the collection of his kinematic models housed at Cornell University. Papers were assembled by Cornell Professor of Engineering Frank Moon during the late 1990's and early 2000's, particularly during research trips to Germany. They include Moon's research notes on Reuleaux and Reuleaux's influence, biography and genealogy; photocopies and transcriptions of letters, essays and drawings created by Reuleaux; Moon's academic papers and professional work on Reuleaux; and research on Cornell's kinematic model collection and other kinematic models. Papers also include material on specific projects, such as the permanent exhibit of Reuleaux's kinematic models at Cornell, and the Kinematic Models for Design Digital Library (KMODDL), an online collection of digitized images and information on kinematics.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Moon, F. C.,1939-; Moon, F. C., 1939-; Redtenbacher, F. (Ferdinand), 1809-1863; Reuleaux, F. (Franz), 1829-1905; Thurston, Robert Henry, 1839-1903; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918; American Society of Mechanical Engineers.; National Science Foundation.
Subjects:
Mechanical engineering; Mechanical engineering--History; Kinematics; Machinery--Models.; Machinery, Kinematics of; Machine design--history; Exhibitions; Science--study and teaching--digital libraries; Centennial Exhibition (1876: Philadelphia, Pa.); Sibley College of Mechanical Engineering and Mechanic Arts
Places:
Cornell University
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Images.; Compact Discs; DVDs; Correspondence; Slides (photographs); Notes; Articles; Photocopies; Printouts; Floppy disks
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Moon, F.C. The Machines of Leonardo da Vinci and Franz Reuleaux: Kinematics of Machines from the Renaissance to the 20th century. Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Springer, 2007.
"The Reuleaux Collection of Kinematic Mechanisms at Cornell University”: http://sections.asme.org/southerntier/pdf/Reuleaux.pdf
KMODDL: http://kmoddl.library.cornell.edu/
Cornell Kinematic Mechanisms images have been digitized and are accessible through the RMC image portal..
SERIES LIST
Series I. Research
By Reuleaux
Reuleaux biography and genealogy
Series II. Models
Non-Cornell Reuleaux Models
Reuleaux Models at Cornell
KMODDL
Other Models
Series III. Moon’s papers and professional work
Series IV. Multimedia and Photographs
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Research
  Funded by the Humboldt Foundation and others, Moon researched Reuleaux at archives such as the Deutsches Museum in Munich. This series includes Moon’s notes and correspondence, photocopies of original documents, and secondary source material. For material relating to Moon’s research on models, please see Series 2.
  - Correspondence on Reuleaux, 1987-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Moon's correspondence with other Reuleaux specialists. Includes a few photocopies of older Reuleaux material.
  - Reuleaux background, correspondence, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence on Reuleaux, photocopy from a biography.
  - Correspondence on Reuleaux, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Moon's correspondence with Germans and German institutions, seeking info on Reuleaux and his models
  - Sabbatic Year. Humboldt Stiftung, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, application, paperwork etc. for the Humboldt Stiftung
  - Reauleux / Thurston (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Photocopied bio of Thurston, and a photocopied Thurston report from the Vienna exhibition (1873).
  - Kinematics of Machinery. Kennedy. 2 lectures., 1881 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photocopy of a book: "The Kinematics of machinery. Two lectures. Relating to Reuleaux Methods..." By Alex B.W. Kennedy, C.E. W/ intro by R.H. Thurston. Reprinted from van Nostrand's magazine.
  - Reuleaux/Thilo/Biomechanics, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Photocopy: Deutsches Museum Vortraege und Berichte. "Naturforschung u. Technik." Vortrag gehalten im Deutschen Muesum am 29. Oktober 1910 von Dr. Otto Thilo.
  - Buch der Erfindungen, 1883-1891? (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Spamer, Otto. *Buch der Erfindungen. Gewerbe und Industrien.* Note on it says it's 1883-1891. Also says "zweite Subskription" (printed) and a note NL069/231.Chapter on clock manufacture "Die Uhrenfabrikation" (269-287)
  - Reuleaux and Chicago Engineering Congress, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Excerpts from magazines regarding Reuleaux and the Engineering Congress in Chicago.
  - Reuleaux bio, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photocopy. K. Mauersberer. "Franz Reuleeaux (1829-1905)". In Banse, G. Wollgast, S. (Hrsg.): *Biografien bedeutender Techniker. Volk und Wissen* Volkseigener Verlag, Berlin 1983, 184-192.
  - Sydney and Melbourne, Reichskanzleramt, 1877-1879 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Photocopies of materials re the Sydney and Melbourne Exhibitions. Includes certificates and letters. Some of it seems to be from the Reichskanzleramt
  - Otto Langen Engine, other images, 1800-1900 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Images of machines and mechanisms
  - Bragastini re Briefe aus Philadelphia, nd (Box 1, Folder 13)
    letter about photocopying mistake
  - Riedler, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Article about Reuleaux "adversary" Alois Riedler in German, by Karl-Heinz Manegold.
  - Thurston: "The Needs and Opportunities of a Great Technical College", 1893 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Photocopied article, originally in *Scientific American Supplement* No 913. This is a reprint.
  - Thurston: "On the Necessity of a Mechanical Laboratory; its province and its methods", 1875 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Photocopied article. "A paper read before the American Railway Master Mechanics' Association. Reprinted from the Journal of the Franklin Institute, December 1875." Philadelphia: WM P. Kildrake, printer.
  - "Professor Reuleaux: Vortrag" H. Wedding article., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Photocopy of the H. Wedding article: "Vortrag gehalten im Verein zur Befoerderung des GewerbfleiBes" Berlin: Leonhard Simion, 1905.
  - Redtenbacher title page, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    A photocopy of the title page for Principien der Mechanik und des Maschinenbaues, by F. Redtenbacher. Mannheim: Friedrich Bassermann, 1859.
  - Bibliography: Reuleaux's writings, (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    From the Deutsches Museum in Munich.
  - Carl Reuleaux articles, 1872-1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    From the Deutsches Museum in Munich. Includes selection from article by Carl Reuleaux (Franz Reuleaux's son): "Auch eine Alabamafrage..." Berlin: Carl Beelitz Verlag, 1872. Also includes another Carl Reuleaux piece: "Von der romantischen zur schoenen Maschine" (publication information unclear).
  - Mannesmann-Rohr, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Article that cites Reuleaux and his significance. "Das Mannesmann-Rohr in seiner Bedeutung fuer das Kunstgewerbe." In *Deutsche Bauzeitung,* no 69-70, 29 August and 2 September, 1891 (article split over two issues).
  - German Telegraph, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    From the Deutsches Museum. Has Reuleaux's name handwritten at the top. * "Wann wurde die erste Telegraphenlinie in Deutschland erbaut?" Ein Beitrag zur Geschichte des Telegraphenwesens* by Sautter. Berlin, 1901. Sonder-Abdruck aus dem Archiv fuer Post und Telegraphie.
  - Reuleaux's influence: Ads for Machinery, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Ads and catalogs selling material influenced by Reuleaux (his name isn't here).
  - Reuleaux: Symbol Notation. Expansion of elements, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Notes on Reuleaux's symbol notation.
  - Reuleaux: Briefe aus Philadelphia, nd (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Notes
  - Munich. Deutsches Museum, Reuleaux Clocks, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Notes, online printouts, correspondence, list of references. Some of it seems is from a the Deutsches Uhrenmuseum.
  - Deutsches Museum, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Brochures, notes, correspondence on the Deutsches Museum and its collections.
  - Reuleaux--DM, Archival Materials, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Notes and material from Moon's research trips to the Deutsches Museum in Munich in 2000-2002. Includes notes, a bibliography, a list of digital pictures taken, list of Nachless (collection) numbers and material about the collection from the archive.
  - W. Goldsmith, A. Dimarogonas, Moll and Reuleaux, 1854-2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Articles by Andrew Dimarogonas and others. Photocopy of work by Moll and Reuleaux: *Constructionslehre fuer den Maschinenbau.* Braunschweig: Friedrich Vieweg und Sohn, 1854; English translation of a few pages. Also includes correspondence with Dimarogonas and Werner Goldsmith.
  - Am Pholosophic Soc., Phil /Reuleaux, 1890-2001 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Research done at the American Philosophical Society; photocopies of Reuleaux correspondence (English), notes, catalog records. Research seems to be from 2001; material from 1890-1969
  - Translations/Summaries: on Reuleaux, 1877-2003 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Translated 2003. Material from Lueders (Wider Herrn Reuleaux!, 1877); Koch (Franz Reuleaux und die Grundung der Mannesmannrehren-Werke, 1969) and others; article on Paris expo. Summaries more than translations. Works 1877-1992.
  - DM: lists of models, original letters, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Notes, phtographs, lists, photocopies from the Deutsches Museum. Research done in 2001
  - Museums: Sci Museum (London), Musee des Arts et Metiers, Smithsonian., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Photocopies, correspondence, notes. Info on collections.
  - Prof Braune--Hannover--Reuleaux lecture, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Powerpoint slides from a lecture on Reuleaux, in German. Given by a Prof Braune in Hannover, sent to Moon.
  - Mechanical Servo Mechanisms History: H.G. Conway, 1867-1954 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Photocopies of two articles.
  - American Machinist excerpts, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Series of blurbs copied from various issues of *American Machinist* that mention Thurston and/or Reuleaux
  - Hans Zopke / Reuleaux, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    In Cassier's magazine.
  - Museums: London, Smithsonian, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Info on various museums with info on Kinematics
  - G. Voigt, (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    About history of Gustav Voigt's home/workshop in Berlin
  - Reuleaux: Phoronomy, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Book on F. Reuleaux--Notes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Notes from Reuleaux Kinematics book and others (no citations).
  - Willis: Principles of Mechanism, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Photocopy of Robert Willis' "Principles of Mechanism: Designed for the use of students in the Universities..." London: John W. Parker.
  - Misc research/articles, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Misc. articles on Kinematics, technology and machining
  - Reuleaux's Machines--Lists, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    . Notes, photocopies of pages
  - American Machinist: Reuleaux Obituary, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    From Sept. 14, 1905. pp 368-370.
  - Scientific American: A. Gradenwitz /Reuleaux Models, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Article from March 21, 1908. "The Mutual Relations of Geometry and Mechanics and Prof. Reuleaux's mechanical Movements."
  - Reuleaux and Sprachverein, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    "Herr Geheimer Regierungsrath, Professor Franz Reuleaux und sein Treiben im allgemeinen deutschen Sprachverein" Braunschweig: Johannes Heinrich Meyer: 1893. Photocopy.
  - Deutsches Museum Reuleaux article, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Photocopied article: "Franz Reuleaux uns die Grundlagen seiner Kinematik." Carl Weihe VDI. In *Deutsches Museum: Abhandlungen und Berichte,* 14. Jahrgang, Heft 4.
  - Kinematic and Dynamic Analysis of the Sanderson Mechanism -- Draft, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    By Raymond Roberts
  - Dubois: Die Schoepfungen Jakob und Alfred Amsler's, (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Misc German articles on Reuleaux, Riedler et al. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Miscellaneous articles and parts of articles in German on Reuleaux and his contemporaries
  - Gears (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Misc articles, notes and drawings
  - Misc correspondence and notes, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Includes a floppy disk
  - Berlin: Severin / Reuleaux, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Correspondence with Ing. D. Severin, articles, printed websites. Visited him in Berlin--Reuleaux scholar
  - Germany: Hotel, air travel, etc., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Itineraries, plane tickets
  - Mechanical Engineering Bios (ASME), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Printouts of Mechanical Engineering Biographies (from ASME).
  - On Reuleaux.'s Animal Kinematics, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Article on Reuleaux's Animal Kinematics. "Animal Kinematics--A Review of a Study of Franz Reuleaux about Restrained Animal Motions." By Hanfried Kerle and Manfred Helm. in M Ceccarelli (ed): *International Symposium on History of Machines and Mecahanisms, Proceedings* HMM 2000. 181-186.
  - Uncertainties in Kinematic Design. A.F.C. Pollard 1933, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Photocopy of 1933 article by Pollard. Actually labeled "Kinematic Design in Engineering."
  - Centennial Expos. Philadelphia, 1876, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Images and list of documents, printed from online.
  - H. Zopke. Biography of Reuleaux, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Notes on Zopke's writings on Reuleaux.
  - Berlin Biographies: F. Reuleaux, A. Riedler, O. Lilienthal, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    A piece on Emil Rathenau
  - Remberger Dissertation--Reuleaux, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Dissertation (in German) on Reuleaux by Sebastian Remberger. Title: *Franz Reuleaux: Ansichten und Selbstverstaendnis eines Ingenieurs in der deutschen Gesellschaft des spaeten 19. Jahrhundert.*
  - German articles on Reuleaux, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Secondary source articles on Reuleaux and his context, all in German
  - Reuleaux research visit, Munich Deutsches Museum, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Notes and research on Voigt and Reuleaux. Includes hand-transcribed letters (Moon's transcriptions) from the Deutsches Museum. Includes Moon's research questions. Moon correspondence, arranging meetings during a research trip in May of 2000.
  - K. Mauersberger, T.U. Dresden, 1985-2001 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Articles by Klaus Mauersberger and others on Reuleaux and technology. Also includes some correspondence with him.
  - Reuleaux-Mitteilungen, Berlin. From Aachen--Dittrich Inst., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Photocopies from a publication called Reuleaux-Mitteilungen, put out by the Reuleaux Gesellschaft
  - Otto, Langen, Wankel engine, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Notes and articles on Otto, Langen and the Wankel engine. Also, general notes on European history.
  - Rotary engines, (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 68)
    From the U. at Karlsruhe. Secondary research.
  - Bevan textbook with Reuleaux diagram, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Photocopies of diagrams from "The Theory of Machines: A Text-book for Engineering Students" by Thomas Bevan. London: Longmans, 1956. pp 144-149. Originally published in 1939.
  - Felix Wankel, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Lookback after his death. Cites Reuleaux's influence on an inventor. From *Frankfurter Algemeine Zeitung,* October 1988.
  - Rotary Engines, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    articles and diagrams
  - A. Stieglitz and Reuleaux, (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 72)
    book chapter on Alfred Stieglitz that mentions him studying under Reuleaux.
  - Reuleaux Curved Triangle, Rolling in a square (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Moon's notes, drawings
  - German Technical Terms, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Glossaries, hand-made lists of terms
  - Kennedy Lectures, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Photocopies of book: *The Kinematics of Machinery. Two lectures relating to Reuleaux Methods.* By Alex B.W. Kennedy. Has intro by Thurston.
  - Reuleaux: Hannover German, Prof Braune., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Mix of primary and secondary source articles on Reuleaux, including one by Hans Joachim Braun. Notes. Material on Deutsches Museum collection.
  - Kinematics: History, 1953-1997 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    Secondary source articles on the history of Kinematics. Articles 1953-1997
  - Reuleaux / Notes; History, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    Notes on Reuleaux, drafts of article on Cornell collection
  - Kinematics of Mechanisms from the Time of Watt (Ferguson), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    Photocopy of pp. 185-230. Contributions from the Museum of History and Technology paper 27.
  - Reuleaux and Math, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    Photocopy from *The Enjoyment of Mathematics: Selections from Mathematics for the Amateur* (Princeton: Princeton U Press, 1957). Info on Reuleaux's curvilinear triangle. Also drawings and notes and a brief article. Gathered 2002.
  - A.B.W. Kennedy--Reuleaux Models, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    Photocopies of article from 1876
  - E. Ferguson--Museums, Models, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    Article "Technical Museums and International Exhibitions" by Eugene S. Ferguson. (print-out off internet; not clear where article was published)
  - Corliss Beam Engine, 1876 (Box 7)
  - Reuleaux on Thomas Calc (Box 7)
    Photocopy of a drawing
  - *Von der Bauakademie zur Technischen Universitaet Berlin: Geschichte und Zukunft, 1799-1999*, 2000 (Box 7)
    History of the institution at which Reuleaux taught. Relevant information marked with a bookmark. Additional relevant photocopies of articles slipped into the back. Will need to be foldered seperately
  - By Reuleaux
    Includes photocopies and transcriptions of original primary source documents created by Reuleaux, such as Reuleaux’s correspondence, publications and drawings.
    - Reuleaux to Thurston letter, 1880's (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Photocopy of letter from Reuleaux to Thurston.
    - Letter Books, Reuleaux:, (n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Typed copies of letters (annotated); also include transcripts by hand, and notes.
    - Letterbooks of Reuleaux, January 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Draft of a Moon piece on Reuleaux's letters, coauthored with Moon's his wife, Elizabeth. Consists mostly of the letters themselves, with some commentary and notes.
    - Rx Letterbooks: Transcribed, January 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      See above.
    - Moon: Reuleaux Letterbooks, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Copy of "The Letterbooks of Franz Reuleaux (1829-1905): A Victorian Engineer." Francis C. Moon and Elizabeth E. Moon.
    - F. Reuleaux / Selected Letters, 1886-1890 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Photocopies of Reuleaux letters from the Deutsches Museum. In German, English, French.
    - Reuleaux Quotes: LdV/Reuleaux Book, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Moon's transcriptions of Reuleaux quotes.
    - Reuleaux: The Machine... (from British Library), 1885 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Full photocopy of *Die Mascine in der Arbeiterfrage.* F.C.C. Bruns' Verlag, 1885.
    - Reuleaux: Das Zentrifugalmoment., 1876 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Photocopy (some pages missing) from Deutsches Museum. In *Verhandlungen des Verein zuer Befoerderung des GewerbefleiBes* 55, 1877, pp. 50-88
    - Reuleaux: Kinematics, 1876. Figures, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Photocopies of figures from Reuleaux's *Kinematics of machinery.*
    - Reuleaux lectures on art, 1897-1898 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Photocopies of articles/lecture on the arts by Reuleaux. (from the Deutsches Museum)
    - Reuleaux lecture: Maschine and Gewerbebetrieb, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Reuleaux lecture: "Ueber den EinfluB der Maschine auf den Gewerbebetrieb" in *Nord und Sued: Eine deutsche Monatsschrift.* Breslau: S. Schottlaender Verlag, 1897. Also from DM
    - Reuleaux lecture: Asian art at the Melbourne Exhibition, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Ueber asiatische Kunst auf der Melbourner Ausstellung. Verein fuer Deutsches Kunstgewerbe zu Berlin.
    - Reuleaux lecture: Zapfenreibung, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      From the Deutsches Museum. "Neue Betrachtungen und Versuche ueber die Zapfenreibung." Published in the *Zeitschrift des Vereines deutscher Ingenieure;* vol 35 pg 932. Photocopied article.
    - Reuleaux correspondence (German), 1862 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Photocopied Reuleaux correspondence. Includes some drawings. Probably from Deutsches Museum
    - Reuleaux reports on exhibitions, 1852-1900 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Reuleaux reports on exhibitions (Paris and Chicago). Plus, photocopies from his quotation book (1852). All from Deutsches Museum.
    - Reuleaux's Reisebuch nach Philadelphia, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Photocopy of selected pages. In Reuleaux's handwriting. From the Deutsches Museum.
    - Reuleaux paper: Das Bahnercentrik, (n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 18)
      "Das Bahnercentrik, ein neuer Bewegungsmechanismus." From *Zivilingineur,* Band 4, Heft 1. (n.d.)
    - Reuleaux lecture: Dampfpumpen, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Ueber Neuerungen an Dempfpumpen und Dampfpumpwerken. Lecture before the Verein fuer Eisenbahnkunde, 1886. DM
    - Reuleaux lecture: Die Ausstellung in Jekaterinburg, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      A lecture about a trip to Russia. Not sure where published. DM.
    - Reuleaux publication: Ueber die Parallelraeder..., 1876 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      *Ueber die Parallelraeder und einege verwandte Mechinismen.* Berlin: G. Hickethier, 1876. DM.
    - Reuleaux: Sektor-Geradfuehrungen, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Describes a bunch of figures that aren't included. DM
    - Reuleaux paper: Sperrwerke, and drawings, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Selected pages from Reuleaux's "Ueber die Sperrwerke und ihre Anwendungen." *Vereins zur Befoerderung des Gewerbfleises* 1877. Berlin: Nicolaische Verlags-Buchhandlung, 1877.
    - Reuleaux: Teledynamic Transmitters, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Translated article: "On New Features in Teledynamic Transmitters." *School of Mines Quarterly,* vol 8, no 2, 1887. DM